You are first episode of 2022.
We're doing an open line night answering your wackiest hardest
most of Stu's questions.
Do you think your uncle is one of the Nephilim?
Are reptilians running your local post office?
Do you want to make a pitch for why unicorns really aren't
monsters?
This is your chance.
Call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855 237 2346.
Before we start taking calls, I just want to mention something
really fun that I found out about recently.
That is that there is this idea that ancient Egyptians worshiped onions.
Have you heard of this Father Stephen?
Yes, I am aware of this.
Of course you are.
And I ran across this because someone asked the question, like, why does Saint John
Christosdom say that Egyptians live in fear and dread of onions?
And I was like, well, that, I'm sure he said that.
And so I looked it up and sure enough there's two different places that he mentions Egyptians
and onions and one of them where he talks about them living
and fear and dread of them. The other one where he actually refers to onions being God,
according to the Egyptians. And that there's actually also references in the Roman pagan writers
Duneau and Pliny, who mentioned Egyptians worshiping onions. It turns out that onions are depicted
all over the pyramids. And it shows up in Egyptian mummification practices that onions were actually
placed in the eye sockets of some of the pharaohs. Yes, they be buried in onion leaves and onion plant.
Yeah, yeah, no, I could
not find and maybe you can add something to this so I get to ask the first question I guess maybe
I could not find actual references to them worshiping onions but it does seem to be the case that
they were doing something something richly with onions and certainly the Romans seem to think
that they were worshiping onions I mean I mean were they offering sacrifices to onions or just
you know, of onions.
Well mostly of onions or a sacred plant.
And if you slice an onion in half and you look at the concentric circles and the shapes,
yeah, that was taken to be a representation of eternity.
Right.
And of eternal life in particular, that's why it gets involved in burials.
But they also used onions for disinfectant qualities.
And since this is a family show, I can't explain how this worked, but as a pregnancy test.
Wow.
Have a pet.
So there you are.
everybody your first weird ancient paganism fact for the night.
I want to say as we go into this I know that even though I'm going to go for some
Mick Foley style cheap pops here even though we have the greatest audience in
the history of any media. Some part in the back of your head father Andrew is
concerned that we might run out of calls. It's true. I just want to assure you
that if that happens that we don't get any calls I have something to talk about
as a backup.
And that is awesome.
If we run out of calls, I'm going to talk about my latest film theory, which is that the movie LA Confidential is a period remake of the 1986 film Dragnet starring Dan Acroid and Tom Hanks.
Huh.
Well, and if Tom Hanks is listening, and calls in, I will lay it all out for him and he can confirm or do not.
Well, Tom, give us a call.
Please call in tonight.
as everybody knows Tom Hanks is an Orthodox Christian, we have Tom Hanks
sightings every year at Holy Week. So Tom please, please call in. But first we are
going to take some calls. So unless they all hung up because they want to hear
the theory. That right? I was worried that could go bad. Exactly. Exactly. So all
right. Well, we're going to take our first call. And our first one is Samuel in
Virginia, who I think we've actually heard from on several occasions. So
Thank you for joining us today.
Samuel, are you there?
Yeah, I'm here. Good evening again.
Good evening, Samuel. Welcome to Laura's
Spirit podcast. What is on your mind?
Well, I on in the second October,
sure I had a question thought you guys
didn't have a time to answer it.
And then I thought.
But out of a couple more questions that day
when I you were when I was on the line,
but so the original one when you were talking about
where was was how.
what we're supposed to make of.
depictions of St. Christopher with the dog's head.
Okay. So, are you asking if that's a werewolf depiction? Is that what you're asking about?
Is that connected to werewolves?
So, I think that it's within this sort of continuum of cannibalism and I mean,
I mean he's often depicted as being a giant as well, right?
So there's this kind of othering.
element that goes along with this. I mean, I've seen it, and I'm sure fathers, Steven,
you have more to say about this, but I've seen it described as well. He was just really ugly,
but I'm pretty sure it kind of goes beyond that, right? So I don't know. I think that there
is a suggestion of that, right, that he may have been involved in that kind of thing in some
level. Obviously, before talking about before his sanctity and so forth, but I don't know.
Father have you looked into the
the the St Christopher with the the the key nine head stuff.
I've I've kind of left that to Paso.
He has all talks about it all the time.
The day after that show, he announced his work with it.
God's dog.
And I thought it was really interesting.
But the next day after I thought of that question, that was announced.
Yeah, yeah, that's where that's where I would go because he could give you the whole.
I mean, he has that Orthodox art journal article we've referred to before.
Yeah.
which is kind of the locus classicus of his discussion of it, but he's done a lot more with it in about it since.
Yeah, it's honestly, it's not something I've ever looked deeply into. I have read some of his stuff about it, but that's about it.
And I am looking forward to getting my own copy of God's dog, which I think is supposed to come out sometime this month or next.
So, all right.
Did he put you up to this? Did he want just the free commercial?
Oh, me or Sam?
either one, not me, not make it sure, make it sure.
No, no money is being no money being changed hands.
I mean, I am paying for my copy of God's dog.
If that's what you mean.
So it goes the other way. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So I don't know if that helps you say, Samuel, but you said you had you had one
other. So we're looking at probably a lot of calls tonight.
We're going to give you just one more.
So when I in the when you were talking about Leviathan kept mentioning this
Kevin had that kept...
think you have the revelation seven hills how to and how that was also an enemy
of the people of God the persecuting them and how much of a connection is
there with it between that and the old testament Leviathan stuff oh that's a
good question I want to know the answer to that.
Oh yes.
There you go. So yeah, so there's a play going on there between the fact that Rome of course
was built on seven hills, the city of Rome. And St. John is very deliberately positing the
present day for him Roman Empire as the current embodiment of
The fuck?
So there's very much a direct connection there because we talked about how, you know, the
monstrous depiction, right, is to convey certain things about the viather, but this is a
spiritual being and a spiritual entity, right?
And so it is a spiritual entity that animates, that animates not just individuals, but also
collectively. People and empires.
cities and so St. Charles very much trying to communicate that the sort of embodiment of Leviathan at that time was the Roman Empire. So this is why revelation both is and isn't about Rome.
Rome. It is about Rome, but it's not just about Rome, right? Because that spirit is embodied,
right? Just like all the demons who are worshiped as the pagan gods by the nation.
they had these multiple embodiments in different places at different times, right?
Yeah. In the same way, Leviathan,
Behemoth, Behemoth, right? They find these embodiments in different places and different times.
Yeah. Is that helpful, Samuel? Yes, it is. Thank you, fathers. All right. Well, thank you very much for calling.
Okay. Next up, we've got Aiden calling from Fort Collins, Colorado. Aiden, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you for having me.
You're welcome. What's on your mind, Aiden?
My question is clarifying one from one of your time-honored sessions of Ruin, Ruin the Bible study.
Breaking Sunday school, as it were.
It has a good name, so I don't know if that works or not. Maybe you guys can come up with something.
You had mentioned that in the Gospel of John that he's using me.
these two terms, feelio and agape and the conversation
with the Lord and that that was really,
that those words were likely just being used interchangeably.
And I was hoping that you could expound on that
on where do you get the information
that comes to you to come to that conclusion.
Yeah.
I've never heard that before.
Yeah, I mean, there's a lot of,
There's a lot of sermons that
that I've been preached on the idea that there's something different going on.
Peter, do you love me?
And then, underneath the Greek is a little bit different.
And even you've got, and I say this with all respect for one of my favorite authors, you've
got CS Lewis as the four loves where he uses that same kind of idea.
So the problem is this.
And this is how I understand it.
um actually me, if necessary, Father Stephen, the problem is that those two words are used
synonymously in a lot of other places, including in the rest of the corpus of the evangelist John.
Right? So if you're going to say that he intends them to be taken in different ways,
then you would need to show that that is his usage or show from something
that that's indicating that, right?
And part of the problem is, of course, that,
you know, it goes the opposite,
like it goes the opposite direction
in other places in his works.
I'm trying to remember a particular example,
like there's one where,
where you know, if you take it that Philea
is just sort of like brotherly, friendly love,
that that would make no sense within the context.
Can you think, am I remembering
that correctly, Father Steven,
or something like that.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, yeah, you're on the right track.
So a lot of people have been taught.
I don't think this happens as much in Orthodox circles, but it may.
But a lot of people have been taught to sort of use this concordance mode of Bible study
where you go and follow a particular word in Hebrew or Greek and sort of follow it through
the Bible.
all the places it's used and you do kind of a
word study, and say, okay, here's what this word means. And then you plug that into all
the places where it occurs. Right. And that's not a normal way to read anything. Right.
Like you would never do that with something other than the Bible. Like you would pick up
my books or Father Andrew's books and say, what are all the ways that Father Andrew uses
the word green in his published books and blog posts? Okay. So here's what Father Andrew
means every time
he says the word green and then go through and plug it in it like you'd never do that right
but a lot of people have been taught to do that with the Bible and what that assumes is that a given word
just has this universal meaning attached to it right which is sort of bad linguistic theory so
words derive their meaning from usage.
And there's lots of examples of this where there's a
word that used to mean one thing and now means another, right? Like at the same language.
Yeah. I mean, grains are good example. Yeah. You can be green with envy, green from sea sickness,
and the sky, you know, can be green because there's a tornado, and the grass is green.
You can sort of a part of a golf course as the green. Right. Or, you know, he's a green recruit,
and they all mean completely different things. Right. And so you have to look at how they use them. So
So there are times
when a particular author uses a word as a technical term, meaning they're doing a particular thing.
So what example of that that we've talked about on the show is when you look across St. Paul's
letters, when he uses the word dead, the noun dead, without an article, he means just dead people.
When he refers to THE DEAD WITH THE ARTICAL, he's referring to deceased crypt-
Right? And the way we discover that is we look at all the places where he uses it with and without the article and we see if there's a pattern.
Right? And then if we see a pattern we say, hey, St. Paul is totally consistent about this. Right? Every time. Right? Then we say, okay, there's a pattern.
a pattern, so these mean two different things. He's using this as a technical term to make
a distinction, right? So you could, if you're going to say, well, I think...
John 21 that he's switching between
Filio and Aeopi to make a distinction.
The way we decide if that's true is we go and look at it and we can just take the gospel.
We just take the rest of the gospel of St. John.
And we say, how does he use those words throughout his gospel?
And is there a pattern?
Right.
And
what you find when you go through and look at how he uses the word is for example when
Christ says to his disciples before his death, the Father himself loves you. The verb he
uses is filio. There you go. That's the thing I was remembering. Right. And he doesn't
mean the Father himself is your friend. Right. He means he loves you. Right. The love of
God right? It's full orbsense. But even more tellingly when he
He talks about the disciple whom Jesus loved, right?
That's all through the gospel, right?
That we believe is referring to St. John himself.
He alternates the verb.
Yeah, so he's not saying that at one point Jesus loved him with unconditional love.
And then at another point he's like, well, we're just friends, John.
Right, right.
Or alternatively, that there's two different disciples.
One who he loved with the full orbed love of God and one who he was just pals with, right?
Right.
But you'd have to say that if those are technical terms for St. John.
If those be two different things, you'd have to say one of those options.
And so it's based on that.
It's based on that.
And another objection that we heard about this after we talked about it.
Because this isn't, I want to be clear, I understand I am ruining a lot of really bull-loved
the material for people.
I do this. So I realize why people want me to be wrong. And what
hold on to it? I understand that. From a lay person perspective,
there's this element of not looking to read something in there,
of course, right? But when when you're used to reading the
Bible in English and you haven't haven't been seminary, but
you speak scripture. And then the Greek is revealed to you, it
seems you know your your budget which can be obviously wrong leads you to
why would he just go from once
the other in the same little
exchange? And you said, ask
this, even if you don't have the
answer, you're asking the question,
why would he do that?
Right.
You know, otherwise just to use
one or the other across that
conversation, if that makes sense.
Yeah. Yeah. And so it turns out,
when you look at St. John's style,
that's just part of his style.
Is that just like in English,
sometimes you'll stylistically,
you don't want to repeat the same
word over and over and over and over again. So you'll use synonyms. But so yeah, I understand
and a lot of times people make really good points on really bad bases. You could preach a
really good sermon where you make a really good point. I've heard this and I've heard them do
that preaching on a text that does not at all say what they're saying it says. Right? There's
some other text that says that but they should have used, right? But and so I'm not trying to
to take away.
the good points that CS Lewis or anyone else made.
Right?
By doing this.
I'm just trying to clarify that one.
But yeah, the other objection we got was about, it says at the end that Saint Peter was
grieved because the third time he asked him, do you love me?
And some people point at that and say, oh, we'll see.
And in English, it does read like that.
The third time he asked him this, that's what grieved him.
But the way Greek syntax works is with Greek.
In English, you tell what part of speech a word is
and how it's functioning in a sentence by the word order.
So our sentences are almost always,
unless it's a question, like subject verb,
direct object, and then whatever else complicates it.
But in Greek, the form of the word tells you,
so you could put it in any order you want.
and
So the words get ordered in order to convey certain meaning.
And so if St. John had wanted to point to the difference in verb in that sentence, he would
have phrased it in Greek that Peter was, that Peter was grieved because the third time
Do you love me? He asked him.
The ask would have been
at the end so that the grieve he was grieved because of what was asked and that's not how
it's phrased. It's phrased. He was grieved because he asked him the third time and then
is the quote of what he asked. Like he keeps asking. Right. Right. And this is what. And
it's interesting because it does kind of almost drive at the city point that's made by the distinction
between the two words. The thrust is the same, that the Indian...
he asks three times, obviously.
Exactly.
You know, do you really?
And so he really needs to die on that hill anyway, right?
Right.
Yeah, he's asking the same question three times,
but use different words slightly to ask the same question.
And that's what that's how to take up too much time.
But I want to make sure that I understand you're also saying,
this is the way that Paul uses these words.
That's not necessarily meaning.
these words have those distinct meetings in different context in the Greek.
Right.
Uh, lecture.
Although it's saying, it's St John in this case.
It's in, it's in St John's.
Well, you talk about the other example.
I think.
Oh, excuse me.
Yeah, say Paul.
Yeah.
Right.
So if St Matthew refers to the dead, you can't just take for granted.
That he means the same thing as St Paul.
You'd have to go through St Matthew's gospel and see how he uses those.
The pattern of his language specifically.
Right.
Okay.
Thank you very much. All right. I love language stuff. So thanks for calling.
Aiden, next we have Gabriel calling from New York. Gabriel, you're there?
Yes, Father, can you hear me? Yes, we hear you. Welcome, Gabriel, to the Lord of
Spirits podcast. What is your question, comment, or complaint?
Okay. It is so crazy to be on the show right now. I'm such a huge fan boy.
It's gonna be okay.
Okay, thank you.
So my question is about the order in hierarchy of demons.
I've heard that demons are chaotic and disorderly and often fight each other, but from my understanding
they also all share one common goal which is to torment and destroy as many humans as
they possibly can.
So why then do they fight amongst each other and if they don't, do they have any sort
of hierarchy or allegiance with each other?
Do they collaborate?
I understand demons are deceitful so they probably try to hide their works in nature from
as much as possible, but is there anything we do know about this?
Yeah, and there's of course that whole issue of where there's this accusation made against
Christ, you know, that he's casting out demons by bails above and he makes the comment, you
know, how can I be working for bails above? Can a house divide it against a stuff stand,
you know?
Yeah.
Which suggests that they're working sort of together.
So here's my take on this since my understanding.
that on the one hand, there are not like ranks of them the way that you see angels laid out in terms of specific roles, right?
There's not this kind of order, the way that, you know, like for instance the St. Dines just lays it out, or even the kind of list that St. Paul uses, you know, when he talks about the unseen powers and stuff.
So there's that.
But on the other hand, as you said, they do have this common goal which...
is they want to drag us into hell with them.
Right?
Yeah.
And certainly there are places in Scripture and in other related literature that talk about
certain demons being like a chief or a leader among them, which could mean a couple of things.
It could mean some level of cooperation, but it could also just mean, okay, this is a
really big one.
Yeah.
So which, and those things can be related, you know, but, but yeah, I mean, I, I
I
I think part of your conclusion that their liars is one of the problems with this.
There's not ranks of hellians all lining up and obeying orders from a captain.
Would that even be necessary if that makes any sense?
That's my...
of hot take on that. Father Stephen, you wanted to add anything to that or subtract or...
Well yeah, the, I mean part of the key is like you look at St. Denis' theory,
api-guide, right? The reason that there are ranks of angels is that we're talking about
degrees and varieties of participation in the divine energies and the works of God, right? That's
That's what puts them in their order.
And that's the...
language that's used for that is sort of how close they are to his throne, but of course
that's analogical language, right, because his throne isn't like a physical chair, right?
Yeah.
So, but that's an analogy, right?
Now, that's the degree to which they're participating in God's works and his creation.
So demons by definition are not doing that, right?
So the sense in which
there is order among the heavenly host and among the saints who join the heavenly host is a sense of order that cannot apply in any way to demons, definitionally.
Right.
But we also have to remember that, I mean, we don't know proportions, but I'll just go ahead and say most of the things we're calling demons.
We're VASC
cosmic intelligences, right? So they're not like dumb, right?
And, and so, you know, for example, I know we've mentioned this, but they're, they're perfectly
capable of playing the long game, for example, right? Like they can do a lot more damage and destruction,
playing a long game over time with a culture.
perpetuating label within that culture, then just throwing into things into
abject chaos and murder, right? Which they should have like a scheme going on
for like hundreds of years. Yes. Is that possible? Yeah. You see that in pagan
cultures. Yeah. Right. Going on for centuries. Right. Where they have people
enslaved, right? To sin and slave to themselves
through idolatrous worship through immorality, right?
Yeah, to create maximum possible evil, essentially.
So does that make some sense, Gabriel?
Yes, that makes a lot of sense.
Thank you so much.
All right, cool.
I just want to say your show is so amazing.
It is so helpful.
And I really thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you enough for this resource.
Like it's amazing.
All my friends watch it now.
So yeah, thank you so much, fathers.
Thank you.
And pray for us, please.
All right.
Alright
Well, we have another call and this is someone calling from
Baton Rouge, the red stick itself.
They're in Louisiana.
This is I believe of he's on the line.
He's are you there?
Yes, there I'm here.
All right. Well, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
What's on your mind?
Yes, I actually recently got engaged.
Some of my question is of course regarding marriage.
And my question is I've heard that the church teaches
that we were made.
Mary and heaven, but I'm not 100% sure if that's true. And if that is true, how does that swear with Matthew
22 when Christ is talking to the Sadduce about the woman who was married to seven brothers and also just
more generally, I kind of I was curious about the spiritual reality of marriage, you know, to become one
flesh, I've heard that my entire life, but I don't really know what that means on a spiritual level.
So I want to answer the second part first and then
and Father Stephen, I'm gonna bump the other one over to you,
although I do know some things about that.
So yeah, what does it mean that the two become one flesh?
Obviously that should not be taken
in an utterly literal fashion,
except for in the sense that it should.
I mean, there is a literal one fleshness that occurs, right?
And that's where marriage is oriented towards child rearing,
towards the creation of children, right?
By God through the couple.
So there's that.
but also there should be this growing intimacy over time.
I've been married now for,
oh boy, 18 and a half years or not,
which means that I'm not an expert at marriage,
but I am now at the stage of my marriage
where I realize I'm not an expert.
And the thing that I often like to tell people,
I served in pastoral ministry for 13 years
and the thing that I would often tell people,
especially you know within the first
year or two typically there are problems that start to arise, right? And people will come
to their pastor and will say, you know, Father, we're fighting all the time. And I mean
this is terrible. And whatever. And I actually knew one priest who had a couple come to him
with exactly that. And he said, Oh, this is wonderful. And the response was, what? And
he said, oh, well, you know, the whole
point of marriage is to reveal your sins so that you can repent of them. So you know, it's
working, which is totally true. And the purpose of marriage from the point of view of the church
besides being for the procreation and raising of children is so that the husband and wife can help
each other to the kingdom of heaven. And some of the way that we do that is that we're
a mirror to each other for the other's sins. I learned all kinds of things about how sinful
I am by being married to my wife and all kinds of opportunities to repent. And so that's
what's going on. And the growing together and intimacy comes as a result of both people
repenting before God and working on that together. And so often people will say, well, we've
We've started having problems.
problems or whatever, you know, and they'll look at their wedding pictures and say,
oh, we were so happy on the day what went wrong.
And I'll say, look, okay, you know, on the day that you got married, you did not have
a good marriage.
You had a wedding.
And it was a great wedding.
But you did not have a good marriage because you were totally new at this.
And you had no idea what you're doing.
You know, you're brand new.
This is day one.
Why would you think you're good at this on day one, right?
the beginning of something.
you're learning a skill, marriage is a skill, right?
So, you know, that's what it means
that the spiritual element of becoming one flesh, you know,
it's about two people working on their repentance together,
right?
So that's the key there.
And before I kick the rest over to Father Stephen,
I want to at least say this as a framing thing,
at least for the way that I think about this question of,
you know, will we be married in heaven?
is
is that even in the modern period,
there are different opinions about this.
Like, I know that Father John Mayan
or, for instance, taught this.
And so from him, it became a lot of people
within the American Orthodox context
learned that from him and so they repeated.
But then there's others that will say,
no, that's not what that means, right?
The way that that position reconciles itself
with Matthew 22, that section of Matthew 22,
is to see that when Christ...
says in the resurrection they know they're married nor are given in marriage but are like angels in heaven
it's a they take it to mean that there's not going to be any weddings in heaven right not that there
won't be marriage in heaven that's the way that they kind of work that out but that's not the only
position on this so now having said that I will kick it over to Father Stephen. Yeah so first I
I just don't want to say that contrary to what father just said, my wife and I have had no problems.
No.
America's sweethearts. You are. I mean not all of us can meet on world of
warcraft. Yes exactly. Right. Exactly. So we have to in answering this question
we have to kind of think a little deeper I think we need we need to think about
what we mean by marriage, right? So, when that question gets asked to Christ...
Okay, what's going on is these are Sadducees asking him who don't believe in the resurrection, right?
So this is being asked not in good faith. This is being asked as a gotcha question, right?
and
The way they phrase it is whose wife will she be because all had her
So it's who whose possession will she be right which of them will will have her as their possession in in the kingdom?
Right? So Christ responds to sort of immediately responding to that, right? But expanding beyond that, right?
So what are the ways in which we think about and talk about marriage and then how would or could they apply in the life of the world to come?
Right? So again, we're not talking about heaven, we're talking about the world after Christ returns.
this is going to become important in a minute.
So one way we think about marriage is sort of this exclusivity, right, that this person
has this intimate relationship and particularly a physically intimate relationship only with
this one other person, right, and no one else, right.
Well, if in the world to come, we're not reproducing, right, and that's not a factor.
So we're not talking about physical...
relations aimed at reproduction of the species, then that factor kind of drops out.
It's just pointless, right?
To say, well, who is this woman going to be having children with?
Well, nobody's going to be having children.
You know, what woman is this man going to be making children with?
Well, nobody, right?
But on the other hand, and I think this is my best reading of my endorph,
which...
It seems obvious if you think about it, right? When we talk about marriage a lot of the time if we think about a couple that's been married for 60 years
Right, you know, they got married in their 20s and now they're in their 80s
They've been married for 60 years. Okay, and we talk about their marriage. What are we talking about?
We're usually not talking about physical exclusivity because at that point there's not a lot of that physical element, right?
At least the part that would be exclusive
family show, right
And what we're talking about is an emotional intimacy, a spiritual intimacy that they've developed
over 60 years of shared experiences and love. Right? So if someone is going to say marriage doesn't
exist in heaven, are they saying, so in the world to come when they're raised from the dead,
in eternal life, all that they've shared together is going to go poof, is going to vanish,
They're gonna forget each other.
They're forget to forget that love. They're forget their children and their grandchildren and the love they have. I mean obviously not right.
Those are the things from this world that are going to last forever right. So that marriage if that's what we're talking about is that intimacy and that love that they share.
That's going to become eternal. That's going to exist in the life of the world to come.
And we have to be careful here. The reason I said I'm stressing
life of the world to come is that there's a lot of nosticism that wiggles its way in here,
especially when addressing this question, because it's a short step from marriage isn't going to
exist. Given the way I just mentioned, we tend to talk about marriage too. We're not going to be embodied
Yeah.
Like biological sex is going to disappear.
Everybody's going to be entrogynous.
or something, all of which you find, I mean straight out of the gospel of Thomas, right?
And even some Orthodox writers slip into this on occasion.
And we have to be wary of that, right?
That we're talking about the life of the world to come, which is everything good in this
world, meaning everything that is the work of God in this world, made eternal and sin
in Expansed.
I'm going to say that.
Does that make sense to you?
Yes, sir. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Awesome.
And congratulations on your engagement.
Thank you, Father.
God grant you.
Call us back in 60 years.
Tell me if I'm right.
How old will we be?
106?
Yeah, something like that.
Yeah.
I'll still be with the show.
I don't know about you.
You may have to get someone else by then.
So, all right, well, we're going to, we're going to get to more of your calls, but first,
we're going to take a short break and we will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Oh
from ancient faith publishing.
The God who reveals himself in Scripture may at times seem to conflict with what seems
right to us.
But the ways of man lead to destruction, by so journeying through this tension, our views
of ourselves, our lives, God and his creation are reshaped and reformed in a way that is truly
real.
Wrestling with Christ as he appears to us in the Bible, will yield his blessing only if
wheel.
ourselves to be molded and taught. We cannot approach the Scriptures to find our own personal Jesus
who conforms to who he may want or even demand that he be. Such a Jesus probably does not exist
and so will avail us nothing. Rather, we must come to know the only Jesus Christ who does exist
and through his grace offers to transform us into his likeness. God is a man of war, the problem of
violence in the Old Testament.
Now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everyone.
You got to hear a little excerpt from Father Stephen's book which, you know, Father Stephen
never wants to hear himself on anything so we know he ran out of the room.
I did.
He totally. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, Father Stephen never listens to any of his own podcasts. I
used to do that actually a little bit more often, but now I don't it's funny now that I do this
professionally. I don't really have time to listen to most of them. I do occasionally listen to some
but but but not not most of them. I just trust the producers. I love you guys. So all right,
well, we're back to your calls and we have Derek who is called in from the great state of Alaska.
So Derek welcome
Lord spirits podcast.
How's it going?
And it's Arkansas, not a lot.
Oh, I see a K on the call board.
So, oh, it should be AR.
Those are slightly different states, slightly different states.
Okay. Well, I was just, you know, Arkansas is the only, I don't know why this is
the case, but it's the only US state east of the Mississippi that, and it is the
I'm a cigarette that I've never been to.
I've been to all the rest.
Okay, well Derek from Arkansas, excuse me. Welcome to Lord of Spheres podcast.
I came from Arizona to make it more confusing, but anyway, so I guess I can build off the
previous question. You know, I have a wife, so we have two kids, we have a third in the
oven. And I've been ever since our first one, I've started paying attention to the culture
more broadly speaking and I've been noticing trends like
stuff like my truth has become the most prevailing kind of idea out there and it's kind of spread like wildfire.
And even the leading theory on basically how the universe has been created when we're speaking materialistically is from some quantum vacuum that's unlimited potential full of energy and chaotic.
And you can never even pin it down until there's an observer.
So it seems like the world kind of in this very chaotic realm where there's no
over our true truth anymore. And I guess if I can pretty much simplify this, I'm wondering
if there's any way that this has happened in the history, if there's something that can
reconcile this from like a Orthodox point of view. My wife and I are about eight months
into the Orthodox Church. We're official Catechumins and yeah, we've been enjoying the journey and found
a lot of peace and clarity. So I'm just wondering for maybe my children, and I'm trying to explain
to them if I can have anything I could point to you and say.
This has happened before. Here's a good example. Think of it like this.
That's a good question. I have thoughts, but I'm going to let you go first, Father,
Stephen, this time. So are you talking about specifically the idea of truth being
completely relative? Yeah, it gets pretty granular where it can, you know, people can, I don't
I don't need to get political, but even...
pronouns basically have millions.
You can't even technically say you have two genders anymore.
Anyway, yeah.
So I'm just wondering if anything's like this has happened.
What's gotten so, you know, fraction is just multiplying
and everything getting a little out of control, you know?
Yeah.
Well, most of human history has been mostly out of control.
What?
It's...
control can also be bad, right?
Yeah.
And so the pendulum is tended to swing.
So we now, because we're modern people,
are sort of very reflective, right?
So we take things like this and we codify them, right?
them philosophically, right? And so...
You have post structuralists are you know writing long books about how you can't convey meaning in language
Right
But we come at that approach and so we we articulate things right so you'll have
people who want to argue you know
So everything is really chaos, and so everyone is free to sort of impose their own meaning on it.
it or everything is chaos and so we need very strong people to come and impose meaning on it
for everyone. In a theoretical way, but though they didn't theorize about it, I mean this has happened
throughout human history just more non-reflectively. The Assyrians, when they went out and cut a bloody
swath across the ancient near-east, conquering and destroying cities.
We're based...
basically imposing their story and their order and their version of the truth on the world through violence.
Right? They didn't have Nietzsche, they're describing it, right?
Or Foucault theorizing about it, but they did it. Right?
And the Romans did it. Right? They made a desolation and called it peace.
as live he says.
So this kind of
of thing has been happening. And so, I mean, you see this in a great place to go with early
Christianity. We already talked about the Roman Empire and the Book of Revelation, right?
But Caesar had a truth, right? About himself, about Rome, about the gods, about culture,
how society was structured, right? He had a truth about humanity, that humanity...
He comes in great dations.
And so slavery is perfectly wonderful because there are some people who are just born unfit
to be free.
They're fit only to be slaves.
There are peasants who are lower than that, right?
And then the people at the top of the society are there because they're just a better sort
of people.
And the emperor is such a great person that he's pretty much a god, right?
And so he had this truth, he was a man and and
One of the first things that Christianity does, if you look at it from the perspective of ideology,
is say, no, that is not what's true. This is what's true. Right? That is not what humanity is.
This is what humanity is. That is not what God is. This is who God is. Right? That is not how the world and society
should be structured, this is how it should be structured.
And the pattern of God
rule over the cosmos. Right and so Christians have really been in the same
position all the way through Christian history is just in a lot of eras which
are the eras that we would might be tempted to look at as the good eras. Actually
aren't the good eras because those are the places where we started to take it
for granted and the places where we haven't been resisting the world are not the
places where the
world has been in pretty good shape. It's just been the places where we've stopped resisting.
Right. So there should always be, right? Saint Peter tells us this, Christian should never be at
home in any nation, in any time, in any place. Until until Christ returns, then we'll be at home
in the world to come until then we should not be at home until then there should be this disjunction
between what the world says is true and what we know is true.
Right. And so I think that's the only way we could approach it with the next generation is yes, I know
You know the internet and this person and that person and this politician and that politician and this
News channel and that news channel are all telling you this is the truth or that is the truth or this other things the truth
but actually Christ is the truth
Right, and then we shape our lives around living out that truth.
those other truths.
Yeah.
What I would add to that is, I know that the word
relativism is used a lot to describe our current situation.
But I've never met an actual real relativist.
Everyone believes that certain things are true.
Even if it's just something like, please don't hit me.
No one thinks that that is good, right?
So everyone deep down believes in some kind of truth.
And usually it's actually not just one little thing.
Usually there's a whole arrangement
of what truth they believe in, right?
And one of the things that Father just said was
talking about the narratives and stories
that were being told as you go.
And he mentions the Assyrians, for instance, saying,
this is what's actually true, right?
And I think that that is one of the most important ways
to understand our current moment.
is that...
Part of it is because living in the information age, we are bombarded with stories of various
kinds that contradict each other all the time, possibly at a high that humanity is maybe
never really seen before.
I'll give you a good example.
I used to actually run a Facebook group dedicated to my town.
And I ran it for actually for about 10 years until I was just like done with it.
And as these things tend to go, but, you know, whenever someone had posed about some minor
crime happening, right, which I mean, crime is always bad, right?
But like, you know, a kid's bike getting stolen or a car getting broken into or whatever,
almost always then people would respond with like, Oh man, what is our town coming to?
It used to be so wonderful.
And now all this crime is happening everywhere.
And I actually knew some of the lo-
police. And I talked with one of them and I said, hey, you know, people are
talking about this kind of thing all the time. I said, is our crime rate actually
like up? And he says, well, actually it's down. Actually it's down. You know, we're
having, you know, a long period of relatively low crime. And I said, well, it seems to
me then that what's actually happening is because we have access to every bad
thing happening everywhere now. We have a very
different impression of the way reality actually is. And it's because we are now receiving
more accounts, more stories, more tales, more narratives than human beings have in the
past, right? At the same time, though, there's always been some level of competition going
on. You know, there's always been some level of people saying, no, this is the truth.
This is what actually happened. Right. I mean, one of the things we've done over and over
on this podcast. This should show how...
the scripture itself is correcting pagan accounts of what's going on spiritually, what's going
on and historically, you know, all this kind of thing, right? And so I think, you know,
I think on a personal familial, you know, parental, you said you guys are, you know, I have
children on that level or, you know, for people with pastors that the key thing is to learn
what the story of the Scriptures, the story of Christianity truly is.
and to learn to tell it well and to keep telling it,
and to, especially if you have children,
to make sure that they're in that story
and that they understand that that's what's going on.
Right, it's not about shielding them from the world,
but it is about shaping them
with what really is actually true.
Right, and when you shape them with that,
I've seen this with my own kids.
When you shape them with that,
and then they encounter some messed up broken,
you know, version, distortion, whatever,
they can see that for what it is, right?
Like a good example, for instance,
like you began by talking
about pronouns, right? And you said, I don't want to get political. And, you know, I'm
a little bit of a scholar of the English language. And I'm like, well, it's not a political
thing at all. This is linguistic. You know, how many, how many genders are there? Well,
linguistically, there's at least three, right? You know, you've got masculine, feminine,
and neutral. But that's language. That's not human beings. You know, English doesn't happen to have,
our has very little and we have grammatical gender left you know we refer to
ships as she, interestingly enough.
But we don't like the French, we don't refer to tables
as she.
We don't think of tables as having gender.
But this is one of the things I think that's,
this is an example.
What is the story of what it means to be human being?
Well, it doesn't include being able to define,
I mean, sex is the traditional word to refer to male
and female amongst human beings, right?
Not gender.
Now we use gender to mean that.
And I totally understand the language changes.
as I could tell people. I know the language changes. That doesn't mean I have to like it.
But nonetheless, what is that all about, right? This sort of gender-bending thing going on,
it's about telling a story that isn't true. That's what it is. It's about telling a story
that isn't true. But I've seen this in terms of people that I've worked with directly.
Someone who, for instance, who starts to say, someone who's clearly female, who starts
to say, well, I'm a boy.
One person that I know of that that's the case, they actually in their life never had any clear sense of
This is what a woman is. This is what a man is in their own home
Right, so in other words they never actually learned the story of what it means to be a man and what it means to be a woman
And so of course they're gonna be confused about that
you know
And so you know, we have to be better storytellers frankly and we have to understand what the story is better frankly
Um,
And, you know, we get so many narratives and so many stories from so many directions all the time.
I think one of the best things that we can do is just turn some of it off.
You know, my job, I work on the internet.
And frankly, I just get sick of the internet sometimes.
Actually on a daily basis a little bit.
But, and, you know, so, like, I've reduced some of my social media engagement just for the sake of my own sanity.
Right?
You know, and...
And I'm going on a run now, but I mean,
I encourage people read to your children.
This has become less of a thing now.
Read good stories to your children.
Read yourself, like spend time reading.
Engagement with good stories is part of the way
that we engage with the story,
that all good stories are ultimately referencing.
Right? So I, like I said, I don't believe in relativism.
I don't think it's really a thing for most people.
It's exhausting to actually try to hold that as a belief
and it's almost impossible.
Everyone believes something, right?
They believe that something is true.
Even if I just don't want to suffer, right?
But the problem is that there's a confusion
and a feeling of a kind of fracturing,
a personal fracturing that occurs
when we are constantly bombarding ourselves
with all of these different ways of understanding.
and seeing the world, right?
And there are good stories and bad stories,
and I don't just mean in terms of quality,
there are good stories and there are evil stories, right?
There are stories that are telling the wrong story, right?
And so we need to become discerning to see
how that works.
But you know, Father Steven's right,
I mean, the whole swath of history
is about stories clashing into each other.
And one of the great claims of Christianity
is to say no wait.
This.
This is the true story.
This is the real one, right?
And that can be uncomfortable to encounter, but the way that we convey and communicate
that story, right, which is what evangelism is, has to communicate it in such a way that
people can receive it.
So it's not just like a competing claim like, oh, we have the true religion.
It's like, okay, well, that's great.
You have the true religion, but are you actually communicating Christ to people?
you know, just saying I'm right.
is not communicating Christ.
Right?
So, I don't know.
That's kind of, that's maybe more than you were looking for.
But it's an important question.
And how do we convey the gospel to people in this very contested experience that we're having?
Which may not well be that different from previous generations.
I mean, certainly the apostles, right? The apostles were living in a very multi-religious, multi-cultural society.
different kinds of religions do they bump into a lot? You know, I mean, like we use the word
paganism, but that really refers to hundreds, if not thousands, of different kinds of religion.
Right? And they were dealing with that. And they were dealing with all the different sects
of Judaism. They were dealing with that. And then of course, then, heresy begins to rise within
Christianity. So you've got that going on. So, you know, that's not to say, you know, quit whining
because we've always been going through this.
but rather to say like let's let's let's get's draw some courage from their experience because we're there we we are there too
like like we're not in a period of christened up
We're definitely not there. We're in a period much more like the apostles in my opinion in my opinion so rant over
Yeah, but that's just like your opinion man
I was worried for a minute there you're gonna go full Henry Higgins, but you pulled back.
No, you pulled back from the...
the brink. It was good. This is not
numb. There are rules. Um, okay.
So was that helpful to you, Derek,
from Arkansas, which I looked up on a
map is in fact, West of the Mississippi.
Yeah. Um, I guess what I could just
pull from that is it appears that human
understanding connects the best to a
story. And I'm coming to aspiring
author myself, like I've got a couple
things are in town already, but...
That would almost even show why when Christ gives us the most profound, you know, teachings
they're in the form of a parable.
So it seems to me that, you know, we must see ourselves within a story and we're aligned
with the story of humankind, the best story that we're ever going to give or ever receive,
I should say. And we should try to stay aligned with that. And that's the importance of the faith.
I think if I could summarize.
You got it, Derek. Absolutely.
Cool. Thank you guys and thank you for two times over two times over. I've listened you guys. I'm a contractor now so I got eight hours every day
Well good for you
Well, thanks for listening and thanks for calling in today. So all right. Well next we have Jeff who is calling from the
great state of Washington
At least that's what it says in the call board. Are you really in Washington Jeff?
I am not in Washington, brother. Father's bless. I
I was in the service so I moved all over.
the place. Your telephone number is from Washington, but I live in North Carolina. Oh, all right.
The old North state. Very good. Yep. You have an old school VPN.
Indie. Okay. Well, before we get into before you get any question, though, Jeff, I have to ask you,
vinegar or the red based sauce. I think before the vinegar, I'm not a native North Carolina,
and obviously with my phone number I definitely love the vinegar you know my
sister moved
before I did and she introduced me to it. And it was kind of novel to me at first, but I really,
really started to like it. My sister's mother-in-law, who is the native North Carolinian, makes a homemade
vinegar sauce and it's to die for. Then you have achieved the proper barbecue. God bless you.
You answered well. All right, what is on your mind, Jeff?
Well I am excited to ask this one.
question because it gives Father Stephen the chance to talk about giants hopefully and we all get excited when he talks about them.
My question is in 1 Peter chapter 3, St. Peter says that Christ descended into Hades and preached to the spirits in prison who were disobeyed in the time of Noah.
And I'm wondering, I've seen multiple interpretations of who the spirits are and I've seen that they are the sons of God who fell in Genesis 6.
and I've seen that they are the disembodied human souls in the
prison of Hades and I am wondering which one is the correct interpretation or is it some other option?
Take it away, Father Stephen. Okay. So, no, this is a key passage on this in terms of the
patristic interpretation of this, right? Because probably the church father who's most famous
for switching to the satellite interpreter.
of Genesis 6, 1 through 4, meaning the interpretation that the sons of God and daughters of men are referring to the lines of Seth and Kane, respectively, is St. Augustine.
And so there were a couple before that. He's not the first one, but he's sort of the pivotal one.
And when St. Augustine comes to that text in St. Peter's
Epistle, he admits he doesn't know what to do with.
it because he basically he interprets it as Christ going and preaching to spirits and
Hades, but St. Augustine just openly admits, I don't know why the ones from Noah's time
would get another chance as opposed to other souls and Hades, right? He says he's got nothing
That's all right.
And to me, that makes the point that this passage is really
pro.
I mean, if you say to Gusta, didn't know what to do, that means this is a big problem for that point of view.
So part of the issue is that people have understood the proclamation that Christ is making there in the sense of the gospel and the gospel in the sense of an invitation.
Yes. Right.
And that's not what the gospel is.
Right.
Interesting.
the gospel is the report of Christ's victory, right?
And that then inspires one to say,
that ends with Christ is returning to judge
the living of the dead,
to judge every man according to his works.
And when you hear that, you say,
what must I do to be saved when that happens, right?
But so it's not an invitation, right?
So the fact that Christ proclaimed his victory
at his descent into Hades and Hades,
This is the end of the video.
not mean he was inviting anyone to repent and believe that's not what the gospel is, right?
That's sort of what we've got in our modern heads. So there is a directly parallel
piece in the Book of Enoch. So check your bingo cards I brought up the Book of Enoch.
That's where a big chunk of...
The first part of the book of Enoch is he sort of goes on this and this is common in apocalyptic literature
He's taken on this tour by angelic guides of
the earth and the heavens and the underworld and
When he's in the underworld he sees the place where the watchers are imprisoned
Where the rebellious angels who were involved in Genesis 6 1 through 4 where they are imprisoned
And they ask, Enoch, hey man, can you go talk to God for us if you're heading up that way
and see if you can get us some mercy?
Now they don't repent, right?
They just say, hey, can you get God to ease up on the punishment, right?
Kind of idea.
And so Enoch says, well, sure, because he's a good guy.
And so when he's in the heavens, he asks...
sort of praise and tries to intercede for them and say,
hey, is there any way you can show mercy on them?
And God basically says, no.
And then he sends Enic back to them
to proclaim to them their doom.
Oh.
Right?
Not only is there not mercy for you here,
but the final judgment is coming for you.
Right. And so if you look at the language and I don't have time right now to argue that first and second Peter are by the same author, that's a
very
Controverted thing in biblical studies, but like I said, I don't have time to go into all that now. It's coming up on the whole Council of God though, so you can listen to it there eventually.
But
Second Peter's even clearer about the angels who send right it's very clear that
is what St. Peter is referring to. And so he's sort of paralleling that story about Enoch,
right? But it's actually Christ who does it, that one of the things he does during his
dissented to Hades, as he's bringing the fathers up out of shoul, up out of Hades, is he proclaims
to those rebellious angelic spirits, their doom, right? Which is proclaiming to them the gospel,
his victory that they've been defeated.
Yeah, as I like to say.
the gospel is not good news for everyone. It's bad news for some. Right? Right. It is because
it's being proclaimed at them. You know? So yeah, I just, I just, sorry, that's my little
witty thing I wanted to add to this.
Go ahead, Father.
Yeah.
So it's what we're doing when we read the gospel facing north, the gospel of Christ resurrection
facing door. We're just repeating that.
Right.
I remember in one of the other episodes,
this is on that topic in traditional Western liturgy.
I went from a Roman Catholic.
I can't confirm that they do read the gospel
on the left side of the altar
and if you're facing east to the left is north.
And that's why they do it.
So even in the Western liturgy, it's the same thing.
Yeah, the traditional ladder in Western liturgy,
they do it all the time.
Yeah, not just, yeah.
Yep.
Oh, the gospel during the liturgy
is read from the left side of the altar facing north.
Yeah.
So yeah.
Exactly.
brilliant.
All right. Well, thanks for calling Jeff from the great state of North Carolina.
Thank you.
You're welcome. So up next we have Emiliaan. And if I'm not mistaken, Emiliaan is calling
all the way from Romania. Is that true?
Yeah, it is. Thanks for having me.
All right. Well, welcome Emiliaan to the Lord of Spirits podcast. And thanks for staying
up really late. I'm sure it must be about what four or five in the morning there in,
sorry about three.
maybe two or three in the morning. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, what is on your mind, Emilian?
So it is somehow related to the last series of Epico on the Old Testament Christology. I really enjoyed
them and after I listened to them I started reading two of the recommended books, namely The Bodies of
of gods and the world of ancient Israel and the
the invisible god by Andre Olov. And so these authors emphasize this idea of the glory of gods,
not as something immaterial like God's plan or that they are honored, but as a kind of manifestation
of God, something like maybe his body or the manifestation of his body, his body which has to
to be shielded from the people.
So God, glory is shrouded inside a cloud or inside a darkness.
And I also remembered that there are many passages in the Old Testament where I think we
can say that the father might be present and he is clouded by this darkness.
So the people would not be in his direct presence and would not take.
And I know that the idea of the glory, the word glory comes from the Hebrew cowhord, I think it is.
And I know it means also weight or mass.
And at some point in a commentary on his blog, other Stephen said that when Moses asked to see God's glory,
He was asking to see the father in his essence, which he could not do only from basic
what exactly is God's glory if it is particular to a certain person of the Holy Trinity or
if the general manifestation of God's work, what exactly is it?
That's a really interesting question. I mean, I know what glory isn't humanly speaking, like,
you know, in terms of like, for instance, the Greek word, the Voxa, which refers to
to reputation or opinion and various kinds of things like that.
things that people say about someone or about something else. But I think this is something
much deeper. So father, he referenced a blog post you made. What's going on? What is the glory of
God? Yeah. Yeah. So part of the difficulty with this is that the English word glory and even the
Greek word doxa is used to translate two different Hebrew words, which are slightly different. And so
that can some
times make it confusing, right? So there's the Hebrew word that you brought up,
cavaud, which refers to as you said, weight, sort of weight or mass or heaviness,
right? Literally, that has that kind of essential quality to it. And that's what,
what summer and orlover are referring to when they're talking about the glory,
being this kind of bodily, kind of substantive thing. But there's also another Hebrew word,
Shikin'a.
which is also translated as glory. And that's more what's used to refer to like the Theophanic
Glory Cloud that we've talked about, right, when the glory of God fills the tabernacle and there's
sort of this flaming cloud, right, that kind of idea of glory, right, or the glory of Christ that
shown like the sun on the Mount of Transfiguration on Mount Teibor. And so those aren't unrelated
concepts, right, but they're not identical.
things, right? So that type of glory, right? The glory of Mount
Tabour is precisely seen by humans who don't die, right? The
say Peter and St. John both talk about having seen his glory
at that moment. And so that's one thing. And then Moses, as you
when he asks to see God's glory,
that's, and we've referred to the
again because that's in the same chapter where it says that he spoke to him face to face,
spoke to God face to face, and then he says, I want to see your glory and God says, no,
if you see me you'll die, right? And that's where it's co-vote. That's where it's this, this other idea.
So I think in both cases, in both cases, this is something that doesn't apply to just one person
of the Trinity, right?
So on the one side with the Shakyana if we're talking about that kind of glory
This is the glory that Christ says in St. John's Gospel. He shared with the Father before the world began
right
And it's that glory that he
temporarily and humbling himself in the incarnation
Right does not display it gets displayed momentarily at Mount Tabor
But then again fully at the ascension
But...
also, if we're talking about God's essence of who he is, we profess that the Holy Trinity
is one in essence.
And so there is a sense in which that does not refer just to the Father, but also to Christ
and to the Holy Spirit.
So there is one-
glory of the divine nature in both senses, right? And yeah, I think that does that answer?
Is that what you were looking for? Or is there something more? Okay. All right.
Can I come with a short follow up? Sure. I mean, you're calling all the way from Romania. So,
So this is your chance.
Oh, we know that God appeared above the Ark of the Common.
during the day of the townman and his site had to be covered by the cloud of reasons otherwise the
high priest would die. So in this case would he see the father? I actually understand that to be
Christ, but that's a longer argument. But I can lay it out a little bit here. I can lay it out a
a little bit here.
I don't know how much of summer you've read, but in the ancient Near East, gods were
seen to have multiple bodies.
I mean, not just that's what idols were, but gods had a liturgical body, is how it's
referred to by scholars, meaning that the god had a hypostasis, a body that was
man.
fast ritually, right within worship. Right. So there is with the with the
cherubim that were in the Holy of Holies, this was the throne of God. Right. And
the God seated upon that throne became visible on the day of atonement. But
also became visible to Isaiah, right, when he received his
call and Ezekiel. And so this is not the only time. But so my understanding is that in
those prophetic visions, right, that they are seeing Christ, but also that in worship, what
we're told in the New Testament is that Christ is in our midst, right, when we worship, right,
to earth.
are gathered. Right? So when we're gathered liturgically, it is Christ who is in our midst.
And so I take that understanding back to the day of atonement. Now I'm not saying if
someone disagrees with me and can make can make another argument, but that's the way
I understand it. Right? I'm not saying this is in like no, this is the only way it could
be but this is my opinion based on those things I just said is that it was crazy.
to appear. Does that make sense to
million? Yes. All right. Well,
thank you very much for calling.
It's it's good to have you. All
right. Well, we're going to take
another quick break and we'll be
right back with your calls. Give us
a ring. Father Andrew Stephen
Daymak and father Stephen De
Young will be back in a moment to
take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of spirits. Give them
a call at 855-237-2346. That's
A.F. Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
but I'm not going to make a marketing appeal to you at the end.
Knowing what the gospel is and being able to teach it to someone else does not require
that you know everything in this book.
But by the end of it, you should know what a gospel is, why there is a gospel at all,
what the gospel is, and what the response to it requires.
Arise, O God, the gospel of Christ's defeat of demons, sin and death.
Now available as an audiobook at audible.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back, everyone.
We really need to put in an inception
in that commercial.
because that is a commercial for a book that you're arguing is not a commercial in a commercial.
It's true.
I didn't make it a commercial though.
That was done to it by somebody else, but it's true.
Thank you for that everybody.
Well, welcome to the third half of our all Q&A episode.
Well, let's get right to our calls.
right to our calls. So we've got Brian calling
at least his phone is from Texas.
But where are you, Brian?
I'm in Texas. I'm here in Austin.
All right. I'm told that Austin is the part of Texas.
It's not Texas though.
Yes, that's very true.
Is it still weird?
Yeah, it's weird, right?
Yeah, okay.
He sure it's about, you know, keep Austin weird.
So yeah.
Yeah, I have cousins in Austin who are from Ohio,
which that's weird.
That Ohioans would move to Texas.
But again, it's Austin.
So I don't know. Yeah, well, it happens to be one of the cities that's the fastest growing in the country so people are coming from all over.
Well, if you bump into them, tell them I said, I, okay, I will do that.
What's on your mind, Brian? Yeah, I've got a part for you, bothers and I just want to say, you know, thank you for the great work that you do.
You're both a blessing to all your listeners. So this two part question, the second part might actually blend into the first.
first but...
You're probably aware that over the last several years there's been this increased public
conversation concerning what the government's calling unidentified aerial phenomena, which
is really UFOs as we would traditionally know them.
And of course that conversation has sparked the possibility that intelligent extraterrestrial
life may be out there or even extraterrestrial life living somewhere in secret here on
the planet.
And of course the
The Bible is silent on all of these issues, of course.
And it's also silent on how to build a combustion engine.
But we know combustion engines exist.
So the secularists seem to view this as a positive thing.
And they look upon this as being the return
of the extraterrestrials who created mankind.
This blends very much into the ancient near east kind
of Anudanki and so on.
And of course, they kind of see this as, you know, the coming of a new Messiah.
And of course, they argue that Christianity would crumble underneath such a revelation
if true extraterrestrials were discovered.
And you're probably aware of, you know, the church is dealt with this in the very distant
past through the conversation of the plurality of worlds and, you know, the possibility of
a planet hopping Jesus who's, you know, in Christ.
on every single planet in the universe,
which really ended underneath Thomas Payne,
who said that was ridiculous.
So, in the modern church,
this is really rarely addressed,
other than the Catholics,
and the Pope and many of his priests have said
that they're ready to evangelize the aliens
when they come,
including baptizing them and welcing,
welcoming them as fellow imagers.
So I'm curious and I know you
have to speculate but how does the orthodox church view the possibility of intelligent extraterrestrial
life and how would it respond to this kind of revelation if it was revealed. And of course the
second part is do you believe Sasquatch is related to the giants either pre or post-flood and if so
are they chimeras? Wow. Yeah. The huge set up on UFOs and then oh by the way Sasquatch
in Eiffelame.
Yeah, well, I've loved your shows on the Giants and they're just so on track with reality
that I just had to ask you that question.
Giant questions are always welcome.
Yes.
It's a rule.
Yeah.
I'll say, okay, the first thing I'll say is, since you asked like, explicitly, what does
the Orthodox Church's view on UFOs?
The Orthodox Church, Qua Orthodox Church, has not, not that I-
I mean, correct me if I'm wrong here, Father Stephen,
but has not put forth any statements at all
about the possibility of the way that we normally think
of extraterrestrial intelligent beings.
I mean, it's funny, like,
is there extraterrestrial intelligent life?
I'm like, yeah, we talk about vast cosmic intelligence
is all the time on this show, you know?
But the idea of like little green men
or essentially something that's sort of analogous
to mankind that's from some other place,
I'm not aware
of the church as the church saying anything about that.
Is there anything like that, Father?
Not that I know of.
Yeah.
There's just individual people saying things.
If there is anything, it would be some individual local church, which would only speak for themselves.
There's nothing across the board from the Orthodox church on it.
Yeah.
Right.
like the idea that we're visited by beings
that are not human but are intelligent.
Like that's in the Bible.
You know, we understand that in terms of the engagement
of mankind with spiritual beings such as angels
and demons and dead people on some occasions, right?
Like this is totally a thing.
And so, I mean, one of the problems is, right?
If you encounter something that you don't know what it is
and it seems intelligent to immediately classify it
in terms of like, I mean I love...
Star Trek and Father Stephen also loves Star Trek.
In terms of the way that Star Trek encounters
these alien life forms,
that's making a whole big set of assumptions, right?
About what it is that someone is encountering.
I'll be honest, when someone says,
oh, if we encounter this,
it's just gonna blow theology wide open or whatever,
I think that's garbage.
Yeah, I
I think it's just garbage because number one,
that's number one you're arguing from a hypothetical.
Like to me, this is like, well, what if God could
make a rock so big that he couldn't lift it?
There's a sort of definitional issue there, right?
So I could hype, I could, you know,
like what if we discovered that there was more than,
you know, that there were more than one Holy Trinity,
that there were six Holy Trinity's,
that would kill theology, wouldn't it?
You know, like, okay, I can...
say stuff like that, but Christianity is about dealing with what has actually been revealed
to us. Right? You know, so there's that as a kind of problem. But again, it's not like
Christianity doesn't have ways of thinking about encountering intelligent life that is
not human. We absolutely do. Like this is not some crazy weird idea that we can't handle.
I don't know.
I don't know father I'm kind of ranting rambling now, but what do you have to say about all that stuff?
Yeah, so if you were a real Star Trek fan
You would have played a final unity and you would know that the reason all of the races are
So similar is that they all come from the same pretend to race that was I remember the cosmos
Yeah, I mean I remember that episode. I remember that episode that's not an episode
It's a video game with the whole there is a TNG
There is, but there is also an epis, so there is an epis.
sort of I think it's next narration that does that where they reference was back to it.
Yeah.
But if you're a real Star Trek fan, you would remember that.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
They find little bits of like DNA.
They find bits of a message within DNA that's seated all over the galaxy and like the
gang on think it's a plans for a weapon.
You know, it comes together and it turns out like it's a hologram message or whatever.
out.
was for a genital race. Yeah. That was contradicted by another episode in which, like,
Warf devolved into a lizard. He did. And he was devolved into apes. So, but anyway,
Star Trek aside. Exactly. Right. Yeah. So it actually, in actuality, if we found a race
of beings on another planet who had a language we...
translate. That would be the ultimate proof that Christianity is true. That's right.
Here's why. Yes, because that would mean that human consciousness, right, is in some way
a universal. That would mean that human nature is a universal. Because another being that's
unrelated, like us in a bat say, right, bat consciousness and human consciousness is
nothing alike.
Right. That's why we can't communicate with bats. Right.
So if an alien race showed up that had a consciousness with the same shape as human consciousness, that would mean human natures in some way a universal and
Only Christianity has that as a base teaching because that's how the incarnation works
Which would mean yes if such a race arrived we should evangelize them
Yeah, okay. Yeah, that makes total sense
There you go. Okay, so Sasquatch. I hope I was just saying Brian, I hope you listened to our our Halloween episode because we actually talked about Sasquatch's a little bit on that but it depends on if
If we're talking about Sasquatch, Qua Pacific Northwest, cryptid in which case he would be a hominid species or if we're talking about Sasquatch, Qua Pacific Northwest,
West.
Yeti archetype
Where he's sort of the old man of the woods
Which then would partake of that kind of giant kind of idea
Well, do you think it's possible? I mean do the fallen lesser gods of the divine council have the ability to manipulate
living entities and use the material of
God's creation to develop their own things
Well,
it would be a DNA thing.
Yeah, I mean, like, this is a nature.
Right. Yeah.
Yeah, I was gonna say like, never could nether,
which we didn't get to, we should do a never could nether
episode.
We didn't get to that, but I mean, if you think about
never could nether, he becomes bestial.
Right?
Because of his sin.
And then he's, you know, he reappends and is restored
and so forth.
So, I mean, that is totally a thing.
Right?
But yeah, it's not like an alteration of nature.
But human beings can be remarkably plastic
in terms of their ability to alter themselves.
So yeah, it's definitely some kind of possibility
in one way or another.
So yeah, is that all you were looking for, Brian?
Yeah, that's all that.
And you know, you had said you were looking for, you know, open questions on anything that's
weird.
So those are the two questions from Weird Austin.
Good for you.
You are our first UFO question, by the way.
Oh, really?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, you're the first one to ask a UFO question.
Well, I think within society, in American society, it's probably going to be a continuing conversation
for another decade.
So I'm sure.
All right.
Well, thank you very much for calling, Brian.
Thank you.
Alright.
Well, we've got another caller from the other side of the Atlantic.
Stace from Ireland.
Are you there?
Stace?
Yes.
Greetings, farce.
All right.
Well, welcome.
Happy to have you on the Lurospheres podcast.
And again, thanks for staying up really late.
It's what?
130 in the morning over there?
Not too bad, yeah.
Not too bad.
If you don't mind me asking, where in Ireland are you located?
So open Balfast.
Oh, oh, you're an oyster man then, huh?
Yeah, from Russia originally actually, so a lot of traveling back and forth.
All right.
Well, you don't, yeah, that thick Russian accent that you've got there.
No, I can sit on, yes.
Oh, nice.
Very good.
All right.
Well, what is on your mind?
So, first I just want to say thanks so much for doing the wonderful show and sharing your
with some others and you definitely helped me bring
bring me back to the phase. So thanks very much for that. So I've been reading through Exodus lately
and just before Moses leaped the Israelites out of Egypt and during the plagues, it's repeatedly
mentioned that Yahweh, Harden's, Ferrell's, Hart. So sometimes it's like passive, it says Ferrell's
heart was hardened but it's implied that Yahweh causes it and then other times it's more active
so it actually says that Yahweh cardened Pharaoh's heart.
And then also a couple of times it says that Pharaoh hardened his own heart.
So I looked around before and I found all sorts of very different answers to this. So some say that
it's that God created like psychological laws and then from that sort of
Pilate Pharaoh to pride and
through his sins just
Let his heart be hardened and then others say there's like a hyperbolic way.
saying the same thing that is to punish Pharaoh. So what's the sort of traditional
understanding of this? Is it to show the always full power to the Egyptians? They keep the actively
hardening this heart. It seems like, you know, he didn't actively harden it. Then at some point,
maybe Farah would have let this or let's go earlier. Like one is...
You know, look at Egypt and destroyed.
You should just let them go.
And then it says, Yahweh, cardin,
it's hard, and he didn't.
So, yeah, which maybe we cleaned up?
Yeah, it's a good question.
I mean, so if you were to do,
you know, if you look at all these accounts from Exodus,
there's actually three different ways that this has talked about.
So on the one hand, it says,
Pharaoh's heart was hardened, right?
So, like you said,
was hardened, right? So that's like you said,
there's a sort of this passive voice.
It just sort of describes it happening.
But it also says that Pharaoh hardened his own heart,
so like Exodus 8.15, when Pharaoh he hardened his heart.
But then it also says that the Lord hardened his heart
and you get God himself saying,
I will harden Pharaoh's heart.
So all of that stuff is in play
throughout the whole Exodus account.
So, and I think one of the problems
is if we try to pick one of those and use it to kind of eliminate the other two, right?
You know, so if you're going to do a, you know, Calvinist reading of it, you would basically say, you know,
well, God and heart and Pharaoh's heart, and that's what all of this really means.
If you're going to take, you know, a more sort of, you know, the opposite view, say, well, this is all Pharaoh's own doing, et cetera.
etc. And then I guess maybe the other would be kind of neutral.
But I mean, there's clearly just from the text of Scripture, it's clear that Pharaoh is doing something and it's clear also that God is doing something.
Right? So, I don't know. That's at least what I'm seeing from the text itself. So, Father Stephen, what would you say about this stuff from Exodus?
Yes, there's a couple of things.
And there is sort of a transition from Pharaoh Harding's own heart to God doing it over the course of the...
narrative. And so the first place we have to start is with the question of what is God doing, right?
So if we come at it from the perspective of God is trying to get Pharaoh to let Israel go.
That's what he's doing. Then yeah, it kind of looks like he's playing games or something because
Pharaoh would have done that, right? But I would submit that that's not what God is trying to do.
Because first of all...
If that's what he wanted to do, he wouldn't have had to do the plagues, right?
You could have struck Pharaoh dead.
You know, there are lots of other ways where he have to get Israel physically out of Egypt.
So there's something else that he's doing.
And before the 10th plague, he tells us what he's doing.
And that he's executing judgment against the gods of Egypt.
Right.
So is this is this like a poshment then sort of taken away for as reason?
Well, Pharaoh is one of the gods of Egypt, right? They see him as well. We can go too far
this because it's a bit that you get into which Pharaoh and all this stuff. But they saw
him as one of the bodies of one of the gods, right? Depending on what exactly historically
you think this took place. Maybe Horace, maybe someone else. But so he's one of the gods
of Egypt and justice, biblically, is not pun-
for crimes. Right? Justice is restoring the correct order, the correct good order of the creation
when it has been thrown out of whack. Right? And so we have a century and a half of the oppression of the people of Israel.
We have the murder of the infant boys of Israel by this Pharaoh.
We have all manner of these things that have happened.
And so the scales are out of whack, right? Pharaoh has exalted himself by humiliating and punishing
and oppressing and exploiting the Israelites, God's people. And so God is going to set that right.
Right? He's going to put things right in Egypt. Right? And so if you're an Israelite who's been
being oppressed and victimized, that's good news. If you're an Egyptian and especially
if you're fair.
that's really bad news, right? And parcel of that with the gods is God showing
that those gods who they've been worshipping and following and really been
enslaved to are not who they should be following, right? And the plagues are
targeted. We may do an episode on this at some point. The plagues are pretty
well targeted at the Egyptian gods. And all of them are
targeted at Pharaoh because Pharaoh's job, the Egyptian word for what I'm calling justice,
it's Mishpad and Hebrew, it's Ma'at in Egyptian was this idea that everything is in its
proper place and functioning properly.
They had the same concept of justice, but that was the Pharaoh's job.
The Pharaoh was basically a priest king whose job was to interact with the gods and rule
over humans and make sure everything stayed in the right place and function properly.
each one of the
the plagues is things going out of whack.
He can't put it back in order.
Even his magicians, this is part of what's going on
in the text, Janice and Janbress, his magicians,
they can make things worse.
It's like, oh look, we can turn water into blood too.
We can't turn the blood back to water.
But we can make more blood.
And there seems to be a limit as well,
so while they can do part two, yeah way.
Yeah, yeah.
They can do a couple of things,
but they're just making it worse.
we could make some more frogs.
like we need them, you know. So yeah, they could create more chaos, but they can't, they
can't put things, put things back in order. And so at a certain point, yes, Pharaoh would
have relented, but notice Pharaoh never repents. As soon as he finally does let the Israelites
go, he changes his mind and chases them down to kill them all, right, for embarrassing
him. So he never repents. This isn't God keeping him from repenting.
This is just God making sure his whole plan plays out to redress the injustice that they've been committed.
That has been committed against his people and by extension against him, right, to make this display
that the gods of Egypt are phonies, not that they don't exist, but that they aren't, they aren't
rightly worshipped as gods. And to make that display not only to the Egyptians, to the Egyptians, to the
the Israelites and when they get
to Canaan, Rahab, sir, about it. The other nations have heard about it. Right. And so he's making
sure that all plays out because he knows Pharaoh isn't going to repent. Right. He might have let
them go after the sixth plague, but he would have chased them down and tried to kill them just like
he did after the tenth plague. Yeah. Yeah. It's interesting. I'm looking at Exodus 14 right now.
And in verse four, this is, you know, God speaking, he says, I will harden Pharaoh's heart and he will
pursue them.
And then this is the part that really struck me.
And I will get glory over Pharaoh and all his hosts.
And the Egyptians shall know that I am the Lord.
You know, so it's just like you were saying, Father,
it's playing out, it's God instituting his justice.
And it's kind of showing like, okay,
I, my glory, the glory of God,
is supposed to be over Pharaoh and all this host.
Pharaoh's been exulting himself, right?
And the Egyptians need to know, as he says,
that I am the Lord, that Pharaoh is not the Lord.
you know, well, that's to hone in on that slightly.
And actually, they will know that I am Yahweh Yahweh.
Yeah, we're right.
Meaning I am he who causes things to be.
Yeah, yeah, right.
As I came to a correct conclusion, but but made the wrong
arguing to get there just like we did earlier with the whole
agape and Philea things.
So yeah.
So would you say though at the point where Yahweh's actively
having his heart he's sort of overrides.
is free will at that point or? Well this gets into the question of what free will is which is a whole big can of worms right?
So, yeah, yeah, I'll try to do this briefly as I can we'll probably do an episode on this at some point but the modern understanding of free will which is I can choose between contrary opposites right I could have Coke or Pepsi right?
Pepsi, right?
it is not the way free will was understood, biblically or by the church fathers.
So will is a function of nature.
So will is sort of a force that drives you in the direction of your nature.
So Aristotle, for example, talks about trees having wills.
A tree has a will and that will, it's not making choices, but that will is sort of the internal
force that causes it to grow and move toward the perfection of its nature.
Tell theology of kind of type of up.
Right, right.
And so, biblically, God overriding someone's free will would be like stopping them from
doing something that they otherwise, that was in their nature to do, right?
Like stunting there, right?
So this wouldn't really be overriding his free will.
would be it would be like clouding as judgment more right more of that kind of
idea right until the process is complete because like I said he never repents
right so this isn't that you know oh he really would have repented he really
would have become a worshipper of Yahweh the God of Israel and all this but God
didn't let him right which is the way Calvinists kind of want to you sorry
Calvinist, why don't you use this thing?
as the whole predestination thing goes.
Right, right.
So they try to make this an issue of salvation,
but that's never in the picture here in Pharaoh.
This is about him taking one particular action
and God, you know, clouding his judgment
so that he waits to take it to a later point.
Right. And with that, as well, then it's mentioned
sometimes that he hired in his own art
to sort of show that that's his intention anyway.
and God sort of not, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, right, right, right, right. And so there's lots of places where God will
intervene, right? I mean Joseph's brothers were contemplating killing him. You know, God didn't let
that happen, right? You know, um, that's not like overriding their free will, right? Or at least we
wouldn't say that in a negative sense, right? That that God, you know, had events take place so that
Joseph would live, right?
Okay, now I think that answers it. Thanks very much.
Well, thanks very much for calling. So we've got Steve now calling from California. So Steve,
welcome to Lord of Spears podcast. Hi, fathers. It's a pleasure to speak with you. Likewise,
likewise. What's your question or comment? Well, I struggled with the notion of correlating gods
absolute knowledge of the future with human-primal agency.
I understand your argument that a God transcends time, he's not bound by time, but for him to know the future as an actuality would require that I also transcend time.
It seems like it is a block model of universe where each moment exists in eternity, like the Hindu version.
And I don't know how to, with Brian from Austin, we talked about logical absurdities that
God is free and powerful to do anything except commit a logical absurdity which I agree
with.
But it seems like absolute foreknowledge of what I'm going to do in the future is a logical
absurdity because I do not, I exist only in time.
I understand God does not, but how would you know my teacher?
as an actuality if I exist at this moment in time, a block model of the universe means
that all moments exist at once.
Okay, I think I understand what you're asking.
So I mean, there's a whole host of things we could say here, but I think one thing that
I would say is, and this is a saying that I love, which is there is no tail without
a teller. And how that's applicable to this is to say that from the point of view of human
beings who are alive in this life, it seems that time moves in a linear fashion, right?
You know, that there's a past, a present future, and I don't know what's going to happen
in the future, and I only have memories of the past and I'm present in the present, right?
But then if you take it out, if you try then to see it.
from God's point of view, which is like what your question is
kind of predicated upon, right?
To say that all points exist already, that's essentially
to say, OK, I'm imagining the way God experiences
or sees all of this.
And this is what that must be like, right?
The problem with that is that's a tale that human beings
are not the teller of, right?
As we like to say, we don't know what it's like to be a bat.
We definitely don't know what it's like to be an angel.
and we certainly...
do not know what it's like to be God.
So it's setting up a logical model in the mind
that then becomes contradictory, especially because we
don't actually have the ability to see things
from that point of view.
We can only imagine what that point of view must be like.
But the problem is that our imagination
doesn't line up with the actual view.
Right.
So, and I mentioned, I began by saying that part of the problem is that it's human beings
in this life experiencing things in this way because human beings who have moved beyond
this life, so for instance the saints, they have a different perspective.
Now they still don't have the same perspective that God does because they're not God, but
they have a perspective that we do not have because we're in this life and they have
shifted in what my dog man expert
would say that they've moved into an angelic time zone, although even then they don't know what it's like to be
that kind of creature, although it's something a little bit more like that. Right, so that's part of the problem is that
it's setting up definitions that are by their nature contradictory and by their nature require us to imagine things
that we don't actually have the ability to see.
right so so you know it's like the mantis shrimp we talked about I don't know
It's been like a year ago, hasn't it now, maybe?
That sees all these colors that we cannot even imagine.
We can sort of detect that they are able to do that
by scientific means, but we still don't actually
even have the ability to see that, right?
You know, we can just imagine it
in a really precise way, I suppose,
but we can't actually see that, right?
So that is at least one way that I want to understand
the
problem of the question that you're asking and why it seems unsolvable from our point
of view. Father Steven you want to, you know, I'm actually me or add or subtract or whatever.
I think that's basically right. So we have to see part of the part of the whole man. I
wonder if people are like if if how is Nagel is monetizing this somehow and people are
downloading the what does it like to be a bad
And he's got this huge spurt from US Orthodox folks.
But see, when we think about what it's like to be a bat,
what we're doing is we're projecting,
what would it be like if my consciousness was in a bat body?
Like if a wizard turned me into a bat?
Because we can only understand things
from our human perspective.
Right.
And so when we try to think of, well, what would it mean
to be like outside of time?
What would that be like?
We, our frame of reference is we tend to,
when we try and think about time,
because it's even more difficult,
we tend to think about it the way we think about space, right?
So like we think about, well, I'm here
in the church office in Lafayette, Louisiana, right?
and right.
I don't know what's going on in London on a particular street right now.
Right?
I have no idea.
What we would say, well, God does.
And so we tend to think of it kind of that way.
Right?
Well, God is in heaven outside of time, but he knows what's happening at all the different
moments.
Right?
Or God is in heaven and he knows what's happening in all the different places on earth.
you
But if we think about that a little more with space,
that's not what we actually believe about God, right?
Because we believe that God doesn't just know what's going on everywhere,
but we say that God is not spatially located, right?
So it's not that God is here in the office with me,
but he does know what's going on in London, right?
He is in London just as much as he's here in this office,
just as much as he's everywhere else, right?
In creation.
And so time wise, we end up with the same thing, but that's even harder for us to conceive
of.
Right.
We, being finite humans, we have to process reality through certain categories that
are embedded in our consciousness and the shape of our consciousness.
And time and space are two of those.
Those are two categories that are embedded in our consciousness.
We can't make sense of the world apart from them.
But that doesn't mean that they're absolute
in the universe.
That just means they're embedded in our consciousness
and we can't think outside of those categories.
We can guess and imagine and analogize,
but that's different than really understanding.
And so even talking about God having a consciousness
is like a weird analogy that breaks down, right?
Saying, what is it like to be God?
I don't know that there is a thing that
it's like to be God. Right? At least analogous to what it's like to be a human or a bat. Right?
Yeah, it's a cat for you. I'd buy one. Yeah. So there's yeah. And so God does whatever that would be
right? Again, this is we're approaching this apophatically. Right? We in Nighatua, right? Where
where we say, you know, we can't have any idea what it's like.
from God's perspective, but we can make negative statements, right?
That his knowledge, what's knowledge for him, which is going to be different than knowledge
for us, but is not going to be contained within those categories, is not going to be restricted
by those categories, right?
So if I as a human, if I as a human knew for certain what you were going to do tomorrow,
then there would be no free will.
Right? Because that's how human knowledge works. Right? If I had human scientific
certain knowledge of what you were going to do tomorrow, there'd be no free will.
Because that's how human knowledge works. So when I say that's not how to
find knowledge works, I mean that's not how to find knowledge works. Because God
is not existing today and knowing the past and the future. Right? Any more than
and he's existing in...
and laugh yet and knows what's going on in London and Tokyo.
Does that make sense, Steve?
And then, well, he participates in time in order to relate to us.
The Bible is full of references of God being jealous and angry
and even surprised, which would be a falsehood if he already knew it.
God is portrayed in the Psalms as being a musician.
music is.
is melody with time. Without time, music makes no sense. It's just a noise. I take great comfort,
the fact that 2 plus 2 equals 4, and 2 plus 2 equals 4 in every corner of the universe, and it
speaks of God's faithfulness to me. It speaks to the fact that God is a God of order. And
Okay.
As I say.
I think the place you're getting hung up, Steve, is that even though the Bible depicts God in
particular ways, and for instance, he talks about God, as he said with music and so forth, God
is not bound by these things. He's bound less. So even though he is a God of order, he's not a
God constrained by order. Right? This is simply the language that we're able to
receive. Right? So, so, you know, God is not, he's not contained in a space. Right? So, so that's,
that's the thing is he's, he's, he's beyond all of that. Right? So it's not going to work out
in any logical way. We have to accept that our human minds are not capable of containing exactly
how God operates. Does that make sense?
Yeah, that's something I-
I've struggled with for probably 20 years.
I've never believed her.
But how does it, is an omniscient being?
But my statement about time is not a comment on God.
It's a comment on me.
How do I feature already known as an actuality?
If I have not yet been there, it seems like a lot of absurd.
It's speaking in Jesus' microwave of burrito so hot
that even he couldn't eat it.
Yeah.
it's
It's because you're saying, so use the word known, known by whom, by God.
We don't know what it means for God to know things. Right? So that's, that's the problem.
And God is present at every moment in time in the same way he's present at every
point in space.
So there's not a past in a future for God.
So technically God doesn't know the future and he doesn't know the past because for
God there is no
future and past. Yeah, it's it's not gonna it can't work out humanly logically. So
that's that's kind of where that's kind of where it goes. It's not something we'll
ever understand in Rapper heads are out. Yeah. The answer is there's no answer. I
unfortunately. I hope on some level that that's that's helpful for you Steve. So
So thank you very much for calling.
All right, well, we're going to move on to our next caller.
We've got Peter who is calling from another one from California. So Peter, welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast.
Hello, fathers. So my question really stems from your episode on spiritual geography. Specifically, if you guys can further explain the differences or maybe no differences between Hades, Cheyenne and hell.
Because, you know, I realize that it seems to me in our English language we use...
these words pretty interchangeably many times.
But as I understood it,
Hades and Shail, which are the same place,
just different names and different languages,
that's the place where one went when they died
prior to Christ's resurrection,
and you're dead, you're just dead there,
you're not being punished or anything like that.
That is where Christ descended to
on his crucifixion and liberated everyone.
And that hell is a different place or even a condition in which one is suffering in the presence of God as punishment after their final judgment.
All right. Hey, this is one that I know.
Somebody's somebody's trying to save 50 bucks. That's what's happening right here.
I'm excited because this is a good English question.
So, okay, so Peter you start out by saying that an English people tend to use hideous
hell and...
you'll interchangeably. And I'm going to begin by saying, that's because they actually are interchangeable.
And one of the things about English is that we have a lot of words that came into English from
different languages. And sometimes the words do really mean the same thing. Now sometimes we tend
to use them differently or whatever. And I have heard people use, for instance, Hades and Hell
So, you know, to...
try to distinguish them from each other.
But here's the thing.
All three of those words,
so Hades comes from Greek,
hell comes from our Germanic inheritance
and she all is a Semitic word.
All three of these words refer to
the place of the dead,
the underworld.
And all three of these words
also refer to deities that have control of those places.
or it may also be said we could say that being dead.
is being in the control of that deity. Right? So like, you know, in Greek mythology, Hades
is the name of the God of the underworld, and it's also the underworld. Right? In Germanic mythology
which includes Norse, Hell is the underworld, and it's also the goddess, interestingly in Norse
mythology, it's a she, who is the lady of the underworld. Right? So, you know, and it goes on and on,
It almost...
every single culture that has a word for the underworld, usually that same word or sometimes
over a closely related word, is the name of the deity that controls the place, right?
And so it's got both.
Now I think in terms of the way that English usage tends to be, hell is a word that is
more commonly known in English than the other two.
And so then there's these images of fire and so on and so forth.
So then some orthodox like to say, well, we don't believe in...
how we believe in Hades, and they're trying to make a distinction between the two, but
it doesn't work because the basic concepts are essentially the same across all these cultures.
And all these words had a history in paganism in addition to their use in scripture and
in Christian theology.
All of these words have that history, so it's a common concept.
But it's interesting.
if you look at what it says in the book of Revelation, it actually says that this, that the
underworld gets cast into the lake of fire. Right? So there's this notion that the place
of the dead gets, then gets placed in this other place, so to speak, which is just specifically
described in fiery terms. Right? So, so I think on one level, you are on the right track
that there is a distinction between those two experiences.
There's a distinction.
between the experience of death before the end.
And then there's the experience of what happens with that place and all those associated with
it after the end, right, after the resurrection, right.
But it just doesn't work out to say that the first is Hades and the second is Hell because
you know, Germanic peoples have been using the word Hell to refer to that underworld pretty
much as long as that word has existed, right.
And the reason why we have...
in English is simply because when the Bible was translated into English, they used the existing
Germanic term that is native to English, right? For that. I mean, the word hell shows up in
Beowulf, for instance, to refer to specifically the underworld, right? Not necessarily a place
of the damned after the resurrection, if that makes sense. So, yeah, so in terms of the English
That's kind of where those things float out.
Father, I don't know if you wanted to add anything on top of that, you know, maybe to
expand on the whole lake of fire thing or whatever.
Well, I do want to point out as we were saying way back at the, toward the beginning of
the show, that words drive their meaning from usage, not their etymology.
Yeah.
So I personally think it sometimes is useful for us as Orthodox people to use Hades instead
of hell because to most Americans, hell does not mean the Anglo-Saxon underwear.
world. Yeah. People now means post medieval post Dante. You're going to help.
Devils poking people with pitchforks. Kind of thing. Yeah. Yeah. Which is just it's just
kind of a misconception of what these concepts even are. Right. So sometimes changing up the
word can help indicate that there's a different concept to play. But also, yeah. The, the,
I mean, essentially, the words are commensurate, like, like Father Andrew said, a lot of times
what you'll find is that individuals
author's orthodox and otherwise. There's a realm of the dead before Christ's
harrowing of Hades. There's realms of the dead after that, what are called the
intermediate state, and then there is right eternal condemnation after the last
judgment. And sometimes different terms will be assigned to those three
different places or realities, right?
by certain authors in order to distinguish them from each other.
So individual authors will use them as technical terms, right,
to refer to one or the other of those,
but on a pure linguistic basis,
like the verbs for love in Greek,
they're roughly synonyms.
Yeah, so is that helpful for you, Peter?
I think so. So have we been, have we really been needing to
to, you know, because I guess I
agree more with what fathers
even work. I'm coming more
from what fathers feel
with saying like the
banishing hell is being a
place of, you know, fire and
brimstone and all that.
So, I mean, should we
really be referring to that
more as the, the lake of
fire than, uh, than hell?
We should be introducing that
more into our language.
I, I tend to, when I'm
talking about after the last
judgment, I tend to refer
to eternal condemnation.
Because the lake of fire
is what I'm talking about
is what?
image that you get in St. Matthew's gospel and revelation that they're picking up from the book of Enic.
There's another mark on your bingo card.
But there's also outer darkness, a place of weeping and asking if there are other images, right?
Gahanna, there are other images for that same reality in the New Testament.
So I use it to use eternal condemnation
and then refer to those various images that are given of what that is.
which are just trying to say this is really bad. Do not want, right? Repent. Right.
Yeah, I like to use, I especially when we're talking about the place of the dead,
prior to all these things, I like to use that phrase the place of the dead. I also like to talk about
the underworld, right? Because especially because those are terms that are not bandied around as much.
And so when you use language that people are not as familiar with, then it gives you the opportunity
to find it for them.
Whereas if you just throw in,
I mean, I don't tend to use the word hell very often.
But like when someone says to me,
well, hell is better than Hades,
or Hades is better than hell.
I'm like, well,
the problem with turning them into
different technical terms like that,
is that then people then go back and look at the Bible
and other texts,
and then they want to apply them as technical terms
when they may not even being used in those texts in that way,
especially when you're talking about translations.
right? So, you know, like in many cases, like the many English
Bibles throughout history, when they see the Greek word,
Hades, they translate it with the English word, hell, because the Greek word,
Hades had not yet made its way into English as the English word, Hades.
Right? It's just because they had this preexisting concept. Yes, it's true.
They're not thinking of the Anglo-Saxon underworld.
more is the pity.
Because the Anglo-Saxon underworld was much more
similar to the Greek underworld in terms of the concept there. And then she will get translated
often as I think it's the grave in the King James Bible. Is that right? The grave.
Yeah, but sometimes hell also sometimes hell.
Sometimes hell.
You get confusing for a modern reader.
Yeah, yeah. So, so I think the key thing is to understand that there is a sort of state of the
the dead prior to Christ. There's other things, other states of the dead after Christ's
of hell slash, hatey slash shield, and then there's what, you know, there's the, after the
resurrection, right? So you've got these different kinds of stages, and then the important thing,
especially when talking about our teaching is to just describe what those look like based on
the scriptures and what the church fathers say about it, you know? And if you have to, if you
are picking words, you know, from these inheritance of words that we have, then define them very, very
clearly as you go because as you said there is
confusion on this point, right? A lot of people have this idea of like there's heaven and there's hell and that you go to one of the other after you die
and hell has those, you know, demons sticking pitchforks in your butt and heaven has angels playing harps on clouds, right?
I mean, all of this is false. Right. So, you know, yeah, we have to have a little bit more robust understanding of what's going on after all of this.
So does that make sense?
Yes, it does. Great. Thank you very much. God bless you.
welcome. Thank you very much for calling. Okay, well, we've got one final
caller for our Q and A episode. And that is Dina who is calling also from
California. So Dina, welcome to the area opagus podcast. Hi father. Thanks for
having me. You're welcome. What's on your mind? Well, to piggyback off of the
last caller actually, I have some questions about the afterlife actually. So
a couple months ago.
So my father passed away kind of suddenly.
He had cancer, but he died of heart attack shortly before he was going to come and live
with us.
And we've been orthodox for, you know, a decade or so, and my dad was kind of a nominal,
non-believer, a lot of things.
But so I didn't really, I was kind of preparing for caring for my family and caring for my father.
They didn't spend a lot of time praying or
praying but caring for his salvation, you know. And so it's been kind of a complicated loss for me.
And my priest was telling me, you know, pray the Jesus prayer. So I've been doing that kind of,
you know, all the time. Every time I think about it, it pray for him and that in some ways it was
very comforting for me and kind of gave me a way to care for him now. And so all
you
to say I do have questions I promise. On the morning of my son's birthday last week I had a dream
and it sort of reminded me a little bit of what we believe happens after we passed
our soul is separate from our body and it was kind of like my dad was sort of reanimating in a way
he was kind of coming back to a body and it started with Justice said and he was kind of wiggling
your space around, getting it to come in.
and then I moved again and everything in his body
eventually came back.
And then I was able to, he called my name and I embraced him
and it was the most wonderful and peaceful
and just wonderful dream.
And I woke up still feeling his warmth and his presence.
So now I'm not saying that the theologically sound dream,
it could be the mind's way of coping.
So my question, then these are two two party questions.
The first question is, what happens when a non-believer passes away and a believer then
prays for that person?
Can they come to know God after death through prayers?
So that's the first question.
Second question, is it common for loved ones who have passed on to manifest in some way
to those that are left behind and have it not be like a demonic experience?
That makes sense?
Yeah
Yeah, these are good questions.
You know, to the first one, the one thing I have many times said to people who have this
concern, I mean, in my own family, I have people who were explicitly atheist.
My grandfather was an atheist.
as far as we know, remained one until he died.
That...
You never know exactly what is going on in someone's heart, especially in their last hours and days.
Right? And of course, you know, in the modern period for many people, those last hours and days are spent in sleep from the point of view of the rest of us.
We don't know what's going on.
I've had multiple experiences in pastoral ministry that indicate to me that there are other things going.
on besides what's simply observable, someone might say, oh well, they never confessed
faith in Christ before they finally went to sleep and then they died later.
I've known a lot of Christians that then became hopeless over their loved ones as a result
of that, of seeing that.
But for instance, there are many times over the years that I went...
and prayed over someone who was dying, you know, at home or in the hospital. And in many cases,
they had hung on for a long time. And then the family finally called in the priest. And I went in
and prayed. And many times, then within an hour or in one case, literally as I was walking out the
room that they finally died, right? Which is an indication that they're...
the prayer that we did together had an effect, you know, that God heard the prayer and something
happened. I mean, I can't say for certain exactly what happened. But I mean, it became so,
like in my first, my first parish I served as an assistant pastor, actually a job that Father
Stephen later had. We had both had the same job, but not at the same time. There was a period in
in which I think there was in space of a week, like three or four people that that exact
same thing happens. And very short order that I prayed the final prayer of the departure
of the soul from the body and the person died within like an hour or less. And it became
like so known throughout the parish that there was one point where the senior pastor actually
joked at a parish council meeting. Now, look, unless you guys vote the way that I want
you to, I'm sitting father injured at your house to pray over you. But yes, father
Olaf was my boss.
A wonderful wonderful.
priest. And so, I mean, there's definitely something going on there that is not visible
to most people, right? So we don't know exactly what's happening inside someone's heart before
the end. And then also, you know, connect it with what you asked about our prayer for them.
I mean, it's the same thing, right?
I mean, you can't repent once you're parted from your body, but other people can repent
for your benefit.
Right?
That is why we pray for our departed.
We pray that God would have mercy on them.
You know, we do the things to draw close to Christ and to advance in holiness and we do
it specifically remembering our loved ones, not because we think that that sort of cancels
out. However they happened to live
their life or we think that we can shoulder all of it for them or whatever, but simply
this is what the body of Christ does. And we do have an effect on each other's salvation.
Right? So we don't know exactly the fate of anybody that we know until, you know, until
the end comes, but we do live in hope for them. And I do pray for my atheist grandfather.
I pray for a lot of departed to my family
who's the state of their soul.
I have.
No idea, you know, but I do pray for them.
And so yeah, it's, this is absolutely a thing.
And it's a good, good thing that we do.
So yeah, I mean, and I think there's reason
to be comforted over it.
Like again, we don't know for certain,
but we do know that this is what we're supposed to do.
I mean, so the advice that you're pre-skeying
to pray the Jesus prayer is definitely
very, very good advice and to pray it for your father, Lord Jesus Christ, and I've got to have mercy on my dad.
You know, so, so yeah. And with regards to your second question, do people sometimes communicate with their relatives? I mean, it is a thing.
It is a thing. You know, by if God wills it, I don't know if it happened in your particular case.
But it certainly is a thing.
So I don't know, Father Steven, I know you have thoughts
about all of this stuff.
Yeah, part of this whole issue is clouded
because even as Orthodox Christians were not really
in an Orthodox environment most of the time.
And so we default to, I mean, especially in the U.S.,
American culture is deeply steeped in Puritan Protestantism.
So we tend to think of salvation
this sort of transactional.
right that there's this thing you have to do and if you do it we may disagree about exactly what it is but whatever it is you have to do it while you're alive and then having done it whether it's praying a prayer or being baptized or whatever particular thing making some kind of commitment if you haven't done it then that's it if you have done it then you're good right right and that's not how salvation works right
Right.
at all. So, and we also don't have the Roman Catholic view of, well, if you die with an unrepentant
mortal sin, like not going to church once on day, then too bad nothing. You can do, right?
We don't have that either. So, for us as Orthodox Christians, all of us are on a continuum,
Right, a continuum sort of runs from beast to God, right? On... on...
in terms of theosis in the one direction and demonization in the other and all of us are somewhere.
Right. And as Father Andrew said, we don't know where any other person is. A lot of times, we're not even attentive to where we are ourselves, let alone be able to figure out where someone else is.
But repentance then is not about being sorry or feeling bad or changing your intellectual
beliefs, right?
repentance is about being transformed and healed and that transformation in healing comes through
the action of God within the human heart with which we cooperate. So this is why, as Father Andrew
said, God works through means. God can do anything He wants directly anytime He wants, but out of His
love for us, he chooses to work through us. Right? He chooses...
to bring salvation to people by us sharing the gospel with them, right? He chooses to show his love and mercy to people by us showing love and kindness and mercy to them.
And he chooses to save people through our prayers. We end every service with through the prayers of our Holy Fathers. Have mercy on us and save us.
Right. So God is very much capable of saving your father through your prayers.
and the prayers of your family. And so
part of saying that prayer is offering those prayers to God not because he needs them and he can't do it without them
Not that you're gonna change his mind and get him to do something he otherwise wouldn't but you get to be a part of that
Right out of his love for you. He's given you the ability to be a part of that
And so that's how I think to think about it in terms of seeing a departed loved one
that literally
happens all the time. Just people don't want to talk about it because everybody will think they're crazy.
But it happens all the time. And the way to judge what is going on there is by the fruits it produces.
If it soes fear and confusion and and and sets you back in your own repentance or causes you to be
less vigilant, right? Like if you if you had had that experience and you had said, oh,
see my dad's okay I don't need to pray for him I don't need to do anything I would say uh-oh whoa
right but if it's if it's an experience that brings peace and love and the joy of Christ then
it's something to be thankful for. Okay yeah. Is that helpful Dina? Yeah that is thank you so much
spoken here. You welcome memory eternal for your
Father. Thank you. God bless you. Well, thank you and thank all of our
callers tonight. It's been a lot of fun talking to everybody. No thanks to Tom
Hanks. We're not calling it. Yeah, hello. I mean, we had all these callers from
California, but not not Tom Hanks. I don't know. Maybe next time. So anyway,
that is our show for today. Thank you, everyone for listening. Thank you for
We're calling everybody.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we'd love to hear from you,
either via email at Lordofspiritsatinchenfate.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits
podcast, Facebook page. We can't respond to everything, but all of it does get read.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific and Pep Strebeck and Jack Vincent are the same character.
So if you are a
On Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews, ratings everywhere.
Most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it and is
going to take it into space in a capsule driven by Jeff Bezos.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
David Straithaire is playing Dabney Coleman's part.
Thank you very much.
Good night, God bless you and we'll be back in a couple of weeks.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian
priests, Father Andrews.
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders and the numbs.